Welcome. Please don't adjust your TV screens or your monitors. I am not Ryan Miller. My name is
Donovan Russell. I am the worship and next-gen pastor here at Canvas Community Church. And it's
my pleasure today to bring you a short message on reflection. Reflection of our past year and of
course moving in to next year. So we're going to talk today. The big question is how have we spent
our time this past year? It's a question that many of us ask ourselves as we look back on our year,
especially with a new year beginning. But don't worry. This is not a message about New Year's
resolutions, which is a good thing since 91% of those resolutions fail in the first few weeks.
And I would even go out on a limb and say that 100% of us would admit that we have unsuccessfully
finished a new year's resolution and are probably getting ready to do the same thing in the next few
weeks. No, today is about reflecting on how and where we've spent our time this past year.
Now, how we spend our time is a great metric to use when we determine what sort of healthy changes
we would like to make in our daily lives. The interesting thing about time is that we all
get the exact same amount of it daily. It doesn't matter if we're young or if we're old, male,
female, happy or sad. We all get the same amount of time. We don't get more or less time daily
because of our socioeconomic status, our jobs or careers, where we go to school or our race.
God gives each and every one of us the same 24 hours every day. We each receive 1,440 minutes daily.
What have you done with yours? Today, we'll look at Ephesians 5, 15 through 17. It reads,
Now, this passage encourages us to live thoughtfully and wisely, being aware of how we choose to spend
our time and aligning our actions with God's will. It's a reminder to stay focused on what truly
matters in our lives and to seek understanding of God's purpose for us. In verse 15, it says,
Be very careful then how you live, not as unwise, but as wise. The new King James reads,
See then that you walk circumspectly, not as fools, but as wise. Now, circumspectly means to walk
diligently, perfectly, carefully, and accurately. You know, this passage, that word definition reminds
me of Jesus and how wonderful God was to make Jesus's earthly father a carpenter. If you've ever
watched a true carpenter work, they are accurate and diligent and very, very careful. They'll put a
joint together, maybe a dovetail joint, and they'll get it all cut down, and they'll put it together,
and they'll see it's a little bit off. And they'll take a tiny piece of sandpaper and just rub a little
bit of it on there to make it perfect, and then put it back together. It requires patience.
Have we walked that way this year? Have we lived diligently, carefully, and accurately? Have we been
persistent and attentive in our walk with the Lord? Psalm 25, 4 tells us,
Show me your ways, Lord. Teach me your paths. How do we find His way and learn His paths? I know that
most of us want to do just that. Learn what God wants for our lives. The best way to do that is by
spending time in the Bible, time in God's Word. Your Word is a lamp for my feet and a light on my path.
See, the Holy Spirit reveals so much to us while reading God's Word that it's difficult to be unwise
or a fool if we spend that time in the Bible. I have found in my own life there's a direct correlation
between consistent time spent in God's Word and having a confidence in the direction of my life.
The Holy Spirit gives us wisdom as we read and pray through the Scriptures. Simply seek after God and
He will give you knowledge and wisdom. Ask Him to show you His ways, to have His heart and loving those
around you. Psalm 14, 2: "The Lord looks down from heaven on the entire human race. He looks to see if
anyone is truly wise if anyone seeks God." He looks to see if anyone is truly wise. How? If anyone seeks God.
Moving on in Ephesians 5 to verse 16, it reads, "Making the most of every opportunity because the days are evil."
Now, none of us will probably ever think that we've made the most of every opportunity we were given.
That's the great thing about God's Word. It'll always challenge us to do better, to be better.
I love the New King James Version translation here again. It says, "Redeeming the time because the days
are evil." It sounds more concrete, more tangible. How have I redeemed my time? I've been given this block
of time. What have I done with it? That's the big question. Time, the elusive Holy Grail. We search for it
in our busy culture and our busy lives. The pot of gold at the end of the rainbow that's always just out of reach.
Sometimes we feel like we never have enough of it. We say, "If only I had more time."
And sometimes we want less of it, or we want to wish it away. Ever talk to the 15-year-old?
Can't wait to turn 16 and get that driver's license?
Sometimes time flies by. One moment I'm holding my newborn baby daughter. And the next moment I'm
walking her down the aisle to be married. And sometimes the clock drags like a springtime
Friday afternoon sitting in the office. We frequently lose track of time or don't know where it went.
Where is the time gone? And then it sneaks up on us. Uh-oh. Time to go. And now I'm late.
We try our best to save time or even to make time. This shortcut will save us two minutes. We can
make up some time here. But no matter what, one thing is for sure. We all spend our time.
How have we spent or redeemed our time this past year? Now, please don't think this is one of those
completely idealistic messages about spending every minute of our waking days doing something
productive and fruitful. It's not. We need to rest. We need to work. We need to spend time with God.
We need to spend time with our families. We need to rake leaves, wash dishes, do laundry. And sometimes,
we need to do absolutely nothing. Now, a great question to ask yourself when you contemplate
how you've redeemed your time this past year is this. Did I have balance in my life? Or did I have
balance in the way that I spent my time? Now, this is an online service, but I just heard the collective
Canvas Community Church family groan, chuckle, throw their hands up and think, "No way. Not really.
I was nowhere near feeling balanced." We know that we are all pulled and driven in so many different
directions with multiple family schedules and events and trips and get-togethers and practices and games
and jobs and music rehearsals and fill in your thing here that it's really tough to find balance in our
daily lives. Our hurried and rushed lifestyles remind me of an old poster that I used to look at when I was
young. It's probably a meme somewhere on the internet right now. But when I was a kid, we would go to the
Apple Blossom Mall and we would beg our parents to let us go into the movie or, I'm sorry, the record
store so I could buy a cassette tape. This is probably even before CDs were really a big thing. We'd walk
around. Usually at one of the ends, you'd see this big rack full of these frames, all these posters in it.
And you could flip through the posters and look at them. I used to love it. There are often funny ones in
there. And there's this one that always made me laugh. It was a wide-eyed, cute little kitten hanging
precariously from a tree limb by just its little claws. The caption said, "Hang in there." Again, as a kid, I laughed.
As an adult, I can relate a little more to that kitten's predicament. And it's not quite as funny.
Many of us feel this way when we look at our weekly and our daily schedules and wonder how we will get it
all done and how we will make it to all the places that we need to be. We often feel like that little
kitten just barely hanging on. Finding some balance isn't easy, but it can be done. I would encourage you in
your quest for balance to start your day strong. Start your day by redeeming your time in the best way
possible. Start your day with your Father in heaven. Start your day with God. Psalm 5:3 reads, "In the morning, Lord,
you hear my voice. In the morning, I lay my requests before you, and I wait expectantly."
Some quality time in the morning for prayer, for Scripture reading, and even a devotion can have a
tremendously positive impact on your day. Starting the morning off with your Creator God gives you the
solid foundation you need to launch into the rest of your busy day. That time with God will strengthen
you, it'll refresh you and prepare you to tackle what lies ahead. Knowing that He is with you, He is there
to guide you, that God cares for you, and He's rooting for you. Now again, I can hear our C3 family groan and
think, "I barely have enough time to get dressed and get to work. In the morning, I don't have time to pack
lunches or even get the kids on the bus. Many of us barely make it to the coffee maker and hit the on
button and pour it in a mug and get out the door." I understand. Truly, I get it. But we all know this
truth. We create time for activities that are important to us. So just start by getting up 20 minutes earlier.
20 of those 1,440 minutes we are given daily. Start there. Every day. 20 minutes of quality time,
talking with God and reading His instructions for our lives. I can't think of a better, more fruitful way
to start your day or a better way to redeem that time that you've been given. Now, as you create your
morning routine with God, slowly increase those minutes. Increase that time spent with
your Father in Heaven. You won't regret it. As we talk about time and our days, it reminds me of the
rocks, pebbles, and sand illustration. Many of you have heard it or seen it before, but it's so
applicable to what we're talking about today. It goes like this. A college professor sets a large jar
in front of his class. He takes several big rocks and fills this jar with them. He asks his students,
"If the jar is full, it won't hold any more big rocks." So they reply, "Yes." Then he takes some pebbles and he
pours it in. They fall down around the big rocks and fill up the rest of the jar in all those spaces.
And again, he asks the class, "If the jar is full."
They again say, "Yes." Seeing no more room in the jar full of rocks and pebbles.
Then he dumps several cups of sand and it cascades and falls into all those little spaces that is left and
fills the jar all the way up. Now for a third time, he asks the students if they think the jar is full.
And through a few smiles and laughter, they again say, "Yes." Now this jar represents your life. Or like we've
talked about this morning, that time that you are given. The big rocks are the important elements.
God, your family, your friends, your passions, and your health. Now the pebbles are the smaller but still
important elements of your life. Your job, your school, your hobbies. The sand is everything else.
All the little stuff. Think material things. Gonna step on some toes here. Binging Netflix, social media, TV,
screen time. You get the idea. Now here's the lesson. If we reverse the order and fill the jar, which again
represents our time, with the sand first, there won't be enough room for the rocks and the pebbles.
If we redeem our time with all the little, unimportant, insignificant activities, the sand, we will never
have enough room for the elements of our lives that we know are important, that we say are important to us.
Time spent with God. Quality time with our family and friends. Even time to rest and reset properly.
Now as we practice the steps we've talked about today, while looking at Ephesians 5:15 and 16,
walking carefully, full of wisdom, redeeming our time wisely, and placing the big rocks in our lives
in their appropriate spots. All of that will align us with the final verse of our Scripture, verse 17,
which says, "Therefore, do not be foolish, but understand what the Lord's will is."
See, prioritizing that time spent with the Lord in prayer and in his word will guard us so we won't act
foolishly and we will have an understanding of God's will for our lives.
Now, as we reflect on the past year, please don't let yourself be consumed by guilt or regret.
Did you miss an opportunity here? Possibly. Could you have done better in this situation? Probably.
Let go of the "I should have done better" moments and embrace the opportunity for renewal.
The end of the year is not just a time for evaluation, it's a time for recommitment.
God is always, always inviting us to start anew, a fresh beginning.
Now, I plan to identify some of the sand in my life and see how much of it I can cut out.
Now, I know I won't remove all of it, but I simply want to create, take some away and create more time,
more space in my jar for the rocks and the pebbles. I want to prioritize how I'm redeeming my time,
making sure that the big things get my attention first and then on down the line.
Now, today and through the upcoming week, seek God's clarity and guidance for the year ahead.
What steps is He calling you to take? What adjustments can you make in your daily life
to redeem your time well and be more aligned with His will?
Can you identify some of the sand in your own life and put it in its appropriate spot
as the filler after your jar is full of all the important items?
As you reflect on what you have done this past year and what God has done in your lives,
in the lives of those around you, please remember this: God loves you.
You are forgiven and you are continually empowered by the Holy Spirit.
May you all enter this new year with your hearts open to His leading, eager to fulfill His purpose in
your lives and in the world around you. I close with one of my favorite Scriptures,
which also happens to be in Ephesians. Ephesians 2:10, "For we are God's handiwork,
created in Christ Jesus to do good works, which God prepared in advance for us to do."
See, God has already created the good works for us to do. It's now on us to go out and do them.
Let's pray. God, thank you so much for this year.
Thank you for the time that we can spend this morning with our family, with our friends.
Hear from your word, Lord Father. Be challenged to look, to recommit, to renew and start fresh next year.
God, I pray that you would help us see what needs to be done in our lives,
what needs to be done in the lives of those around us, and be your hands and feet, Lord. God,
help us search out those good works you want us to do. Empower us to do them, Lord Father,
and let us do them with a glad, happy heart, serving you and serving your people. God,
we love you and thank you for caring for us, for creating for us, for wanting to be in our lives.
In Jesus' name we pray. Amen. All right, Canvas Community Church, as Pastor Ryan loves to say,
go in church, peace. Have a great year.